{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Scholars have conjectured possible relatives of this man based on the fact that his last name means “deer” in Narragansett. This man, who used the alias Michael Johnson, had been a slave of Deacon William Brown. This man’s body lay in state in Faneuil Hall after men under Thomas Preston opened fire on a crowd that had been throwing snowballs. For ten points, name this Native American and African American patriot, the first person killed in the Boston Massacre.",
      "answer": "Crispus Attucks"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler broke with the Soviet Union and opened up his economy to the West under his policy of Infitah. Though he had planned the surprise attack Operation Badr, this leader was assassinated by Islamic Jihad because of his diplomatic efforts with Menachem Begin, with whom he shared the 1978 Nobel Peace Prize. For ten points, name this successor of Gamal Abdel Nasser as President of Egypt who signed the Camp David Accords with Israel.",
      "answer": "Muhammad Anwar el-Sadat"
    },
    {
      "question": "Kazimir Malevich’s 1915 painting of a Black one of these things supported an essay explaining a shift “From Cubism to Suprematism.” Two of these things appear in the background of a Rembrandt self portrait that may be a reference to a legend about Giotto. One of the earliest works of abstraction, Hilma af Klint’s Svanen, is a colorful group of concentric ones of these shapes. Medieval European art frequently depicts God creating the world by using a compass to draw, for ten points, what basic, round shape?",
      "answer": [
        "circle",
        "Black Circle",
        "disk Note: Legendarily, Giotto was asked by Pope Benedict XI to demonstrate his artistic skill, so he drew a perfect circle with a single motion."
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Causes of this war included the execution of the crew of the Virginius. During this war, hundreds of soldiers died thanks to Russell Alger’s cut-rate rations in the Embalmed Beef scandal. Frederic Remington was told to furnish pictures so that William Randolph Hearst could furnish this war, which was supported by yellow journalism. The sinking of the USS Maine helped trigger, for ten points, what war between the US and a European falling power in 1898?",
      "answer": "Spanish-American War"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1947, this team’s GM Billy Evans wrote “TRUST YOU WILL FIND YOUR NEW CONNECTION A MOST PROFITABLE ONE” in an antisemitic telegram telling Jewish-American star Hank Greenberg he’d been given away to the Pittsburgh Pirates. In 1912, a player for this team shouted “I don’t care if he got no feet!” when fans tried to get him to stop beating a handicapped man who had been heckling him; that player’s career hits record was broken by Pete Rose. The notoriously racist Ty Cobb played over two decades with, for ten points, what Major League Baseball team in Michigan?",
      "answer": [
        "Detroit Tigers",
        "either",
        "both names"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was assassinated by Cassius Chaeraea after attempting to permanently move to Alexandria. This man may have gone mad after the death of Julia Drusilla, leading to rumors that he appointed Incitatus as a state official. This son of Germanicus was affectionately called “little boot” by the legions. Tiberius was succeeded as emperor by, for ten points, what Roman emperor who supposedly made his horse a consul?",
      "answer": [
        "Caligula",
        "Gaius Caesar",
        "Gaius Julius Caesar Augustus Germanicus",
        "do not"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During a visit to this country, one psychologist stated that his only goal was to “catch sight of a porcupine;” that trip led Sigmund Freud to conclude that this country “was a mistake.” A psychologist from this country developed the ideas of habit, will, and stream of consciousness in his book Principles of Psychology; that man also wrote the book Pragmatism. For ten points, name this home country of William James, who was a professor at Harvard.",
      "answer": [
        "United States of America or USA",
        "America"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Investigations of this event included the Hoey Report, which was criticized by the U.S. Navy’s Crittenden Report. A slur by Everett Dirksen inspired the popular name for this event, in which President Eisenhower’s Executive Order 10450 led to numerous firings of “subversives” from the State Department. Roy Cohn was accused of being closeted during, for ten points, what 1950s “scare” regarding homosexuals in the US Government?",
      "answer": [
        "Lavender Scare",
        "Lavender Lads, the slur by Dirksen"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this city, after the deaths of Echol Cole and Robert Walker in garbage compactors sparked a sanitation strike, the Mason Temple became the site of the “I’ve Been to the Mountaintop” speech on April 3, 1968. The next day at this city’s Lorraine Motel, James Earl Ray shot and killed the orator of that speech. Martin Luther King Jr. was assassinated in, for ten points, what second-largest city in Tennessee?",
      "answer": "Memphis"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country, the only non-microstate in Europe that did not sign the Helsinki Accords, executed a priest for baptizing a child in 1971, four years after it declared itself the world’s first atheist state. Hundreds of thousands of concrete bunkers were built in this country during the Cold War under Enver Hoxha, who replaced King Zog as its leader. For ten points, name this Balkan country where, in 1991, communism fell in Tirana.",
      "answer": "Albania"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader, who defined peace as “respect for the rights of others,” confiscated Catholic Church land in the Law of the Nationalization of the Ecclesiastical Wealth. This man’s Minister of the Interior, Francisco Zarco, created the rurales, a mounted police force that was expanded by Porfirio Diaz. This man’s family fled to New York after an invasion by Maximilian I, but he was restored to power in 1867. For ten points, name this Zapotec president who led the Liberals during the Reform War and opposed the French invasion of Mexico.",
        "answer": "Benito Pablo Ju´arez Garcia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During Juarez’s presidencey, Ignacio Zaragoza won this May 5, 1862 battle that delayed the French takeover of Mexico. This battle is annually commemorated on Cinco de Mayo.",
        "answer": "Battle of Puebla"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these facilities in Sobibor was demolished after Alexander Pechersky and Leon Feldhendler organized a revolt. Methods developed in the Aktion T4 program were used in these facilities. Operation Reinhard involved the construction and use of these facilities, where Zyklon B was used; the operation was named for Reinhard Heydrich. Treblinka, Buchenwald, and Auschwitz were sites of, for ten points, what facilities built by Nazi Germany to carry out the Holocaust?",
        "answer": [
          "Nazi German extermination camps",
          "concentration camps",
          "equivalents like death camps"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The poison gas involved in Zyklon B is based on this compound, which was first isolated from the pigment Prussian blue.",
        "answer": [
          "cyanide",
          "hydrogen cyanide"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This politician published the autobiography Why Not the Best? shortly before declaring to run in the primary elections. During his term, this President oversaw the evacuation of Love Canal and the passing of the Superfund law. This man’s namesake doctrine sanctioned the USSR for their invasion of Afghanistan, and he boycotted the Moscow Summer Olympics shortly before he lost re-election. The 2002 Nobel Peace Prize was awarded to, for ten points, what US President who was succeeded by Ronald Reagan?",
        "answer": "James Earl “Jimmy” Carter, Jr."
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Carter and his wife Rosalynn have increased public awareness of this Georgia-based charity that uses a volunteer labor force to build housing around the world.",
        "answer": "Habitat for Humanity International"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At this location, the Marquis de Lafayette’s willingness to kiss a queen’s hand helped calm tensions during the October Days after cannons from the Hotel de Ville were dragged here by angry women protesting the price of bread. Charles Le Brun helped supervise the construction of this facility, which featured gardens designed by Andre Le Notre and a Hall of Mirrors. Paris was replaced as the site of the royal court by, for ten points, what French palace complex built by Louis XIV [14]?",
        "answer": "Palace of Versailles"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Women’s March on Versailles, or the October Days, was a food riot of this social class. Over 90% of France was part of this class; the clergy and nobility held power as the two other classes.",
        "answer": "Third Estate"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This agency changed its policies after an incident involving four year old Charlotte May Pierstorff. In 1970, this agency allowed its workers to be given collective bargaining rights after a nationwide strike involving 210,000 employees. People were forbidden to use this agency for obscene purposes by the Comstock Laws. Until 1971, the leader of this agency was a member of the Cabinet. For ten points, name this government agency for which Ben Franklin served as the first postmaster general.",
        "answer": [
          "United States Postal Service",
          "USPS",
          "US Mail"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Charlotte May Pierstorff changed USPS policy by performing this action. Henry “Box” Brown escaped slavery via the Adams Express Company and this process.",
        "answer": [
          "they mailed themselves",
          "descriptions relating to living people being shipped in the mail"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A legend relates that these people came into existence after a namesake region revolted against Agis I. People born of these women were labeled as nothoi. An earthquake in the Eurotas Valley allowed these people to launch a revolt. Members of the Krypteia could kill these people without repercussions. These subjugated farmers made up the bulk of the population of ancient Laconia. For ten points, name this class of slaves in Sparta.",
        "answer": "helots"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Most helots worked as farmers, but some worked as servants in this education system for Spartan boys.",
        "answer": "agoge"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After land mines and missiles were found at Ascot House, this man dismissed another leader as “a cobra in the house.” The Gukhurahundi massacres, whose name means “the early rain that washes away the chaff,” were carried out by this leader’s army. In the 2013 elections, this opponent of Joshua Nkomo claimed he would “fight like a wounded animal.” After sacking Emmerson Mnangagwa, this man was placed under house arrest. For ten points, name this leader of Zimbabwe from 1980 to 2017.",
        "answer": "Robert Mugabe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mugabe led this Zimbabwean political party, which shared power for the first time in history in 2008 after Morgan Tsvangirai’s [chang-ee-rai’s] Movement for Democratic Change won 100 seats in parliament.",
        "answer": "ZANU-PF"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event led to the resettlement of 18,000 children in the Cuban resort town of Tarara. The Liquidators group was formed to bulldoze pine trees after this event, which required the building of a concrete sarcophagus. A high incidence of thyroid cancer was discovered among people in the vicinity of this event, which created the Red Forest. Pripyat was evacuated as a result of a failure in reactor 4 during, for ten points, what 1986 nuclear disaster in Soviet Ukraine?",
        "answer": "Chernobyl nuclear meltdown or disaster, etc."
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mikhail Gorbachev advocated for this policy of “openness” in the wake of Chernobyl and other incidents of Soviet non-transparency.",
        "answer": "glasnost"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Colonial Women",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Wife of John Adams, who advised him “Remember the ladies...”",
          "answer": "Abigail Adams"
        },
        {
          "question": "First First Lady of the United States, who oversaw Mount Vernon.",
          "answer": "Martha Washington"
        },
        {
          "question": "First English child born in the New World; she disappeared with the Roanoke Colony.",
          "answer": "Virginia Dare"
        },
        {
          "question": "Seamstress who legendarily made the first American flag.",
          "answer": [
            "Elizabeth “Betsy” Ross",
            "Elizabeth Griscom",
            "Elizabeth Ashburn",
            "Elizabeth Claypoole"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Nickname of a woman, probably Mary Ludwig Hays, who heroically assisted at the Battle of Monmouth.",
          "answer": "Molly Pitcher"
        },
        {
          "question": "Freed slave and poet who met “his Excellence, George Washington” in 1776.",
          "answer": "Phillis Wheatley"
        },
        {
          "question": "British spy who assisted her husband, Benedict Arnold, in his plot to betray West Point.",
          "answer": "Margaret “Peggy” Shippen"
        },
        {
          "question": "Quaker who was hanged in June 1660 after a brief staged reprieve, becoming the third Boston Martyr to be executed.",
          "answer": "Mary Dyer"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Eighty Years’ War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Empire that held the Netherlands as a personal union prior to the Eighty Years’ War.",
          "answer": "Spain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynastic house from Austria that, at the time, ruled that country.",
          "answer": [
            "Habsburgs",
            "Hapsburgs"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Largely German empire of which the Netherlands was officially a part until 1648.",
          "answer": [
            "Holy Roman Empire",
            "Sacrum Imperium Romanum",
            "Heiliges R¨omisches Reich"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of the Dutch Revolt, the father of the Netherlands, who was assassinated by Balthasar G´erard.",
          "answer": [
            "William I",
            "William of Orange",
            "William the Silent",
            "William the Taciturn",
            "Willem de Zwijger",
            "Willem van Oranje"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Kingdom that lost control of the Malabar Coast and the Cape of Good Hope as part of a war with the Dutch.",
          "answer": "Portugal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fireships that worked as floating bombs during the Siege of Antwerp; ships of the same name fought the Spanish Armada.",
          "answer": [
            "hellburners",
            "hellebranders"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty, part of the larger Peace of Westphalia, that established the Dutch Republic in 1648.",
          "answer": "Peace of Mu¨nster"
        },
        {
          "question": "Confederation of Dutch nobles led by Willem Bloys van Treslong that seized Brielle after losing access to British ports.",
          "answer": [
            "Sea Beggars",
            "Watergeuzen",
            "Gueux de mer"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Modern Asian Leaders",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "North Korean family that advocates Juche and includes Supreme Leader Jong-un.",
          "answer": "Kim family"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader who announced the One Belt, One Road Initiative as China’s current President.",
          "answer": "Xi Jinping"
        },
        {
          "question": "Successor of Manmohan Singh and BJP party leader who became Prime Minister in 2014.",
          "answer": "Narendra Modi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founder of the National League for Democracy who won the 1991 Nobel Peace Prize under house arrest in Rangoon.",
          "answer": "Aung San Suu Kyi"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who resigned in 2019 and now lends his name to the capital of Kazakhstan.",
          "answer": "Nursultan Abishuly Nazarbayev"
        },
        {
          "question": "Liberal Democratic Prime Minister whose economic policy is based on “three arrows.”",
          "answer": "Shinzo Abe"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lebanese Prime Minister whose father’s 2005 assassination sparked the Cedar Revolution.",
          "answer": "Saad Hariri"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ruling family of Bhutan whose “Dragon King” Jigme Singye abdicated in 2006.",
          "answer": "Wangchuck family"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This musician included tracks like “Sonnet for Sister Kate” and “Sonnet for Caesar” in a twelve-part suite based on the work of William Shakespeare. Paul Gonsalves played a 27-chorus solo in the middle of “Diminuendo and Crescendo in Blue” at the 1956 Newport (20 pts)",
        "Jazz Festival, where this bandleader was begged to stick to a curfew. Juan Tizol and saxophonist Johnny Hodges played in this man’s orchestra. Billy Strayhorn’s (10 pts)",
        "“Take the ‘A’ Train” was a theme song of, for ten points, what jazz pianist and composer of “Mood Indigo” and “It Don’t Mean a Thing (If it Ain’t Got That Swing)” who led the Cotton Club Orchestra?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Duke Ellington",
        "Edward Kennedy Ellington"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man, who was accused of cannibalism in the Coffin Handbills, won a battle after the opposing soldiers forgot to bring ladders to climb the fortifications that this man had constructed. During that battle, this man was assisted by the French (20 pts)",
        "pirate Jean Lafitte. This man defeated the Creek at Horseshoe Bend, the last battle of the Red Stick War, and he defeated Edward Pakenham in a battle that occurred (10 pts)",
        "after the Treaty of Ghent ended the War of 1812. For ten points, name this general who won the Battle of New Orleans before being elected President in 1828."
      ],
      "answer": "Andrew Jackson"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this battle, the losing commander devised an attrition strategy known as Operation Judgement. To end this battle, Charles Mangin helped one side recapture a location that the losers captured without firing a shot on this battle’s third day, (20 pts)",
        "Fort Douaumont. Control of the Meuse Heights was a central goal of Erich Falkenhayn during this battle, which began roughly three months prior to the Battle of the (10 pts)",
        "Somme. The German plan to “bleed [the French] white” failed at, for ten points, what longest battle of World War I’s Western Front?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Verdun"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A god from this civilization was syncretized with Hermes to form Hermes Trismegistus, the purported author of the Hermetic Corpus. While at this civilization’s Siwa (20 pts)",
        "oasis, Alexander the Great proclaimed himself to be a god. Worship of the syncretic god Serapis in this civilization was instituted by (10 pts)",
        "Ptolemy I, and worship of the sun disk Aten here was instituted by Akenaten. For ten points, name this civilization whose people worshiped the pharaohs as incarnations of Osiris and Horus."
      ],
      "answer": "ancient Egypt"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This author discussed the election of Donald Trump in the essay “Mourning for Whiteness.” This author’s hometown of Lorain, Ohio is the setting of her debut novel, in which marigolds ominously fail to bloom and (20 pts)",
        "Pecola longs for the title symbol of whiteness. In the aftermath of the Whitewater scandal, this author described Bill Clinton as the first black president. (10 pts)",
        "Escaped slave Margaret Garner inspired a novel by this author in which a murdered baby returns from the Ohio River as a ghost. For ten points, name this American Nobel laureate who wrote The Bluest Eye and Beloved."
      ],
      "answer": "Toni Morrison or Chloe Anthony Wofford Morrison"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man attempted to secure power by forcing his nobles to swear the Salisbury Oath. This ruler’s suppression of the revolt of Edgar the Aetheling was so destructive that the campaign became known as the (20 pts)",
        "“Harrying of the North.” This man accounted for landholdings in his territory by ordering the compilation of the (10 pts)",
        "Domesday [“doomsday”] Book. The Bayeux Tapestry depicts the death of Harold Godwinson at the hands of this man’s archers. For ten points, name this Norman duke who was crowned King of England after his 1066 victory at Hastings."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "William I of England",
        "William the Conqueror",
        "William the Bastard",
        "William of Normandy"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A message sent by William Draper to the overseer of this effort included a request for “seventy Dakotas.” After the success of this effort, a parade was thrown in New York City to celebrate Lucius (20 pts)",
        "Clay. On a day called Black Friday, low visibility conditions saw an abnormal amount of participants in this effort fail to arrive on schedule at (10 pts)",
        "Tempelhof. “Raisin bombers” helped improve children’s morale in, for ten points, what American supply effort that avoided a Soviet blockade of a divided German city?"
      ],
      "answer": "Berlin Airlift"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Escalation in tensions before this war included a bombardment ordered by Lord Napier and a seizure of stockpiles by Charles Elliott. As a result of successful operations in this war, the name “devil ship” was given to the iron warship (20 pts)",
        "Nemesis. During this war, Chusan and the Bogue Forts on the Pearl River Delta were captured. To end this war, the (10 pts)",
        "Daoguang Emperor accepted the Treaty of Nanking, granting Hong Kong to Britain. For ten points, name this 1839-42 war in China sparked by the trade of addictive narcotics."
      ],
      "answer": "First Opium War"
    }
  ]
}